Guide to the Tarleton Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Tarleton family papers
1830-1888
1861-1869
MS 481
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Correspondence, autograph album, genealogical notes, photographs and miscellaneous papers of the Tarleton and Lightfoot families of Alabama. The major figures represented in the collection are Robert Tarleton, his wife Sarah Bernard Lightfoot Tarleton, and Sarah Bee Ross Lightfoot. Most letters were written by Robert Tarleton and date from the Civil War period. The papers also contain an 1834 letter from Marquis de Lafayette to the President of the French Chamber of Peers.
Tarleton family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Robert M. Tarleton and Mrs. A.R. Colvin in 1940 and 1942.
Scope and Contents
The Tarleton Family Papers consist of letters, photographs, and miscellaneous items of the Tarleton and Lightfoot families of Alabama, primarily from the Civil War era. Most of the letters were written by Robert Tarleton to his mother and his fiancée and wife while he was at military camps during the war and doing business away from home in the early years of Reconstruction. The photographs show Tarleton and his wife, their parents, and a few other people.
The Tarleton Family Papers were given to Yale University Library by Mr. And Mrs. Robert M. Tarleton and by Mrs. A. R. Colvin in 1940 and 1942.
Additional Tarleton family photographs are located in the Historical Picture Collection (MS 713):
- Margaret (Brack) Tarleton
- Robert Tarleton
- Robert Tarleton and another young man
- Captain Jack and Sarah (Mrs. Jack) Eggleston
- Alfred Ross, borther of Sarah Bee (Ross) Lightfoot
- Unidentified young man
Biographical / Historical
Robert Tarleton (1838-1868): doctor; studied medicine in New York City; served in the Confederate Army during the Civil War; taken prisoner and escaped, 1864.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Families; Medicine; Confederate States of America -- History; Southern States; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Autographs; Physicians; Soldiers; Brack, William; Cleburne, Patrick Ronayne, 1828-1864; Cole, Susan Tarleton; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834; Lightfoot, Sarah Bee Ross; Lightfoot, William B.; Tarleton, Robert, 1838-1868; Tarleton, Sarah Bernard Lightfoot; Lightfoot family; Tarleton family; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory, 1830-(1861-1869), 1888
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous papers
    - Robert Tarleton
      - Letters to Margaret (Brack) Tarleton (Mrs. George W. Tarleton) [mother], 1861 (Box 1)
      - Letters to Sarah Bernard (Lightfoot) Tarleton [fiancée and wife], 1863-1868 (Box 1)
      - Legal and financial papers regarding the estate of William Brack, 1867-1868 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous family papers, 1834-(1861-1869) (Box 1)
    - Marquis de Lafayette: A.L.S. to the President of the Chamber of Peers, [France], concerning a favor he wished done fro some American friends, 1834 (Box 1)
  - Sarah Bernard (Ross) Lightfoot: autograph album, 1830-1834 (Box 1)
  - Robert Tarleton
    - Admission passes for medical instruction in New York University and the Medical College of Alabama, 1859-1861 (Box 1)
    - Bible, prayer book, and Princeton class book, 1869, undated (Box 1)
    - Wallet, jackknife, undated (Box 1)
  - Sarah Bernard (Lightfoot) Tarleton: testament, 1864 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified daily memorandum book, 1856 (Box 1)
  - Genealogical notes, [post-1868] (Box 1)
  - Johns Hopkins University commencement program, showing Robert M. Tarleton as a candidate for the B.A., 1888 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - William Bernard Lightfoot, father of Sarah Bernard (Lightfoot) Tarleton, [ca. 1850s-1860s] (Box 1)
    - Sarah Bee (Ross) Lightfoot, mother of Sarah Bernard (Lightfoot) Tarleton, [ca. 1850s-1860s] (Box 1)
    - George W. Tarleton, [ca. 1850s-1860s] (Box 1)
    - Margaret (Brack) Tarleton, [ca. 1850s-1860s] (Box 1)
    - Robert Tarleton, [ca. 1850s-1860s] (Box 1)
    - Sarah Bernard (Lightfoot) Tarleton, [ca. 1850s-1860s] (Box 1)
    - Backyard of house in town, with unidentified children and nursemaid, [ca. 1850s-1860s] (Box 1)